June 29, 2016.
29 يونيو 2016.
My dear fellow citizen:
مواطني العزيز،
I write to you today,
أكتب إليك اليوم،
to you who have lost in this era.
إليك يامن ضعت في هذا العصر،
At this moment in our common life,
في هذا الوقت من حياتنا المشتركة،
when the world is full of breaking
حيث العالم مليء بالإنكسار
and spite
والضغينة
and fear,
والخوف،
I address this letter
أوجه هذه الرسالة
simply to you,
ببساطة إليك،
even though we both know
رغم أننا سويةً نعلم
there are many of you behind this "you,"
أن هناك مخاطبين كثر خلف كلمة "أنت"،
and many of me behind this "I."
والكثير من الأشخاص مثلي حين أقول "أنا".
I write to you because at present,
أكتب إليك لأنه في الوقت الحاضر،
this quaking world we share scares me.
هذا العالم المهتز الذي نتقاسمه يخيفني،
I gather it scares you, too.
وأعتقد أنه يخيفك أيضاً.
Some of what we fear, I suspect,
بعض مما نخشاه، كما أشك،
we fear in common.
نخشاه جميعاً.
But much of what we fear seems to be each other.
ولكن أكثر ما نخشاه، على ما يبدو هو بعضنا البعض.
You fear the world I want to live in,
تخاف من العالم الذي أريد أن أعيشه،
and I fear your visions in turn.
وأخاف رؤاك في المقابل.
Do you know that feeling you get when you know it's going to storm
هل تعرف ذاك الشعور الذي يخالجك حين تعلم أن هناك عاصفةً قادمة
before it storms?
قبل أن تعصف؟
Do you also feel that now,
هل تحس بذلك أيضاً الآن،
fellow citizen?
مواطني العزيز؟
That malaise and worry
عدم الارتياح والقلق
that some who know
الذي يعرفه البعض
feel reminds them of the 1930s?
وهم يشعرون وكأنه يذكرهم بالثلاثينات من القرن الماضي؟
Perhaps you don't,
ربما لا تعرف،
because our fears of each other
لأن خوفنا من بعضنا البعض
are not in sync.
ليس متناسقاً.
In this round, I sense that your fears of me,
في هذه الجولة، أشعر أن مخاوفك مني،
of the world that I have insisted is right for us both,
من العالم الذي أصريت أنه المناسب لكلينا،
has gathered over a generation.
قد تفاقمت مع مرور الأجيال.
It took time for your fears to trigger my fears,
أخذت مخاوفك وقتاً لتثير مخاوفي،
not least because at first,
لأن في بداية الأمر،
I never thought I needed to fear you.
لم أكن أدري أنه علي أن أخاف منك.
I heard you
سمعتك
but did not listen,
لكنني لم أنصت،
all these years when you said that this amazing new world
حين قلت في كل هذه السنوات أن هذا العالم الجديد الرائع
wasn't amazing for you,
لم يكن رائعاً بالنسبة لك،
for many of you,
للعديدين منكم،
across the industrialized world;
في شتى أنحاء العالم الصناعي،
that the open, liquid world I relished,
ذلك العالم المنفتح والسلس الذي استمتعت به،
of people and goods and technologies flowing freely,
حيث ينتقل الناس والبضائع والتقنيات بكل حرية،
going where they pleased, globally,
ويذهبون حيث يرغبون، حول العالم،
was not, for you, an emancipation.
لم يكن، بالنسبة لك تحرراً،
I have walked through your towns
تجولت في مدنك
and, while looking, failed to see.
وبينما أنا أنظر، لم أر شيئاً.
I did notice in Stephenville, Texas,
لاحظت في ستيفنفيل في تكساس،
that the town square was dominated
أن ميدان المدينة كان محتلاً
by one lawyer's office after another,
بمكاتب محاماة واحداً جنب الآخر،
because of all the people rotating in and out of the prison.
لأن كل الناس كانوا يتناوبون على الدخول والخروج من السجن.
I did notice the barren shops in Wagner, South Dakota,
لاحظت المحلات المهجورة في واغنير في داكوتا الجنوبية،
and the VFW gathering hall
وفي ردهة تجمع في إف دبليو
that stood in mockery
والتي تقف بسخرية
of a community's dream to endure.
من الصبر اللازم للحلم الجماعي.
I did notice
لاحظت
at the Lancaster, Pennsylvania Wal-Mart,
في لانكاستر، بينسلفانيا وال مارت،
that far too many people in their 20s and 30s
أن عدداً كبيراً من الناس في العشرينات أو الثلاثينات من عمرهم
looked a decade or two from death,
بدو وكأن بينهم وبين الموت عقداً أو عقدين،
with patchy, flared-up skin
ببشرة غاضبة غير سليمة
and thinning, stringy hair
وشعر رقيق كثيف
and browning, ground-down teeth
وأسنان صفراء آيلة للسقوط
and a lostness in their eyes.
وضياع باد في أعينهم.
I did notice that the young people I encountered in Paris,
لاحظت أن الشباب الذين قابلتهم في باريس،
in Florence, in Barcelona,
في فلورنسا، وفي برشلونة،
had degrees but no place to take them,
لديهم شهادات، لكن لا أماكن لتوظفهم،
living on internships well into their 30s,
يعيشون على فترات تدريبية حتى في الثلاثينات من عمرهم،
their lives prevented from launching,
حياتهم محرومة من الانطلاق،
because of an economy that creates wealth --
بسبب اقتصاد يخلق الغنى --
just not jobs.
ولكن لا يخلق وظائف.
I did notice the news about those parts of London becoming ghost quarters,
لاحظت الأخبار عن تلك الأجزاء من لندن وقد أصبحت أحياء تسكنها الأشباح،
where the global super-rich turn fishy money into empty apartments
حيث يحول أثرياء العالم أموالهم المشبوهة إلى شققٍ فارغة
and price lifelong residents of a city, young couples starting out,
فيدفع سكان المدينة المتأصلون الثمن، ويغادر الأزواج الجدد،
out of their own home.
يغادرون بيتهم.
And I heard that the fabric of your life
وقد سمعت أن نسيج حياتك
was tearing.
قد تمزق.
You used to be able to count on work,
اعتدت الإعتماد على عملك،
and now you couldn't.
لكنك لا تستطيع ذلك الآن.
You used to be able to nourish your children,
كنت تستطيع أن تطعم أطفالك،
and guarantee that they would climb
وتضمن أنهم سيتسلقون
a little bit further in life than you had,
أعلى أكثر في سلم الحياة مما تسنى لك أنت،
and now you couldn't.
لكنك الآن لا تستطيع.
You used to be made to feel dignity in your work, and now you didn't.
اعتدت الإحساس بالفخر في عملك
It used to be normal for people like you to own a home,
كان من الطبيعي بالنسبة للناس مثلك أن يمتلكوا بيتاً،
and now it wasn't.
لكن الأمر ليس كذلك الآن.
I cannot say
لا يمكنني القول
I didn't know these things,
أنني لم أكن أعرف هذه الأشياء،
but I was distracted
لكنني كنت ملهياً
creating a future in which we could live on Mars,
بخلق مستقبل سنعيش فيه على المريخ،
even as you struggled down here on Earth.
رغم أنك كنت تناضل هنا على الأرض.
I was distracted
كنت مشغولاً
innovating immortality,
بالإبداع في الحياة الأبدية،
even as many of you began to live shorter lives than your parents had.
رغم أن العديد منكم أصبحوا يعيشون حياة أقصر من تلك التي عاشها آباؤكم.
I heard all of these things, but I didn't listen.
سمعت كل هذه الأشياء، لكنني لم أكن أنصت.
I looked
نظرت
but didn't see.
لكنني لم أكن أبصر.
I read, didn't understand.
قرأت، لكنني لم أفهم.
I paid attention
انتبهت
only when you began to vote and shout,
فقط حينما بدأت في التصويت والصراخ،
and when your voting and shouting, when the substance of it,
وعندما كان تصويتك وصراخك، حينما كان فحواه،
began to threaten me.
بدأ يشكل تهديداً لي.
I listened only when you moved toward shattering continental unions
أنصت فقط حين تحركت لتقسيم الاتحادات القارية
and electing vulgar demagogues.
وانتخاب دهماء مبتذلين.
Only then did your pain become of interest
حينها فقط أصبح ألمك مثيراً للاهتمام
to me.
بالنسبة لي.
I know that feeling hurt
أعرف أن هذا الشعور بالجرح
is often prologue to dealing hurt.
هو غالباً مقدمة للتعامل الجارح.
I wonder now
أتساءل الآن
if you would be less eager to deal it
إن كنت ستصبح أقل حماسةً للتعامل معه
if I had stood with you
إن وقفت معك
when you merely felt it.
حين بدأت بالكاد تشعر به.
I ask myself
أسأل نفسي
why I didn't stand with you then.
لم لم أقف معك حينها.
One reason is that I became entranced
سبب واحد أنني أصبحت مفتوناً
by the gurus of change,
بصانعي التغيير،
became a worshiper of the religion of the new for novelty's sake,
وأصبحت عبداً لدين كل جديد بحق الحداثة.
and of globalization and open borders
والعولمة والحدود المفتوحة
and kaleidoscopic diversity.
والتنوع المتلون.
Once change became my totalizing faith,
حالما أصبح التغيير هو إيماني الكامل،
I could be blind.
كان من الممكن أن أكون أعمى.
I could fail to see change's consequences.
فشلت في رؤية تداعيات التغيير.
I could overlook the importance
كان من الممكن أن أغفل أهمية
of roots, traditions, rituals, stability --
الجذور والتقاليد والطقوس والإستقرار --
and belonging.
والانتماء.
And the more fundamentalist I became
وكلما أصبحت أكثرتعصباً
in my worship of change and openness,
في عبادتي للتغيير والانفتاح،
the more I drove you towards the other polarity,
كلما قدتك نحو النقيض التام،
to cling,
للتشبث،
to freeze,
للتجمد،
to close,
للانغلاق،
to belong.
والانتماء.
I now see as I didn't before
أرى الآن أكثر من قبل
that not having the right skin or right organ
أن عدم امتلاك البشرة أو العضو المناسبين
is not the only varietal of disadvantage.
ليس النوع الوحيد الذي يشكل النقص.
There is a subtler, quieter disadvantage
هناك نقص صامت وهادئ
in having those privileged traits
بامتلاك تلك الخصائص المتميزة
and yet feeling history to be moving away from you;
لكنك تشعر أن التاريخ يبتعد عنك،
that while the past was hospitable to people like you,
بينما كان الماضي مرحباً بالناس أمثالك،
the future will be more hospitable
سيكون المستقبل أكثر ترحيباً
to others;
بالآخرين،
that the world is growing less familiar,
حيث أن العالم أصبح أقل حميمية،
less yours day by day.
ولم يعد عالمك يوماً بعد يوم.
I will not concede for a moment that old privileges should not dwindle.
لن أتنازل للحظة عن فكرة أنه ليس على الامتيازات القديمة أن تتضاءل.
They cannot dwindle fast enough.
لن تستطيع التضاءل بالسرعة الكافية.
It is for you to learn to live in a new century in which
سيكون عليك أن تتعلم كيف تعيش في قرن جديد حيث
there are no bonuses for showing up with the right skin and right organs.
لا مزايا للتظاهر بلون البشرة أو الأعضاء المناسبة.
If and when your anger turns to hate,
وحين يتحول غضبك إلى كره،
please know that there is no space for that in our shared home.
فلتعلم من فضلك أن لا مكان لذلك في بيتنا المشترك.
But I will admit, fellow citizen,
لكنني سأعترف، مواطني العزيز،
that I have discounted the burden of coping with the loss of status.
أنني أزلت عن كاهلي زوال الموقع الاجتماعي.
I have forgotten
نسيت
that what is socially necessary can also be personally gruelling.
أن ما هو ضروري اجتماعياً يمكن أن يكون قاهراً عى المستوى الشخصي.
A similar thing happened
حدث نفس الشيء
with the economy that you and I share.
للاقتصاد الذي نتقاسمه أنا وأنت.
Just as I cannot and don't wish
لست أستطيع ولست أتمنى
to turn back to the clock on equality and diversity,
أن أعيد عقارب الساعة للمساواة والتنوع،
and yet must understand
وعلى الرغم من هذا علي أن أفهم
the sense of loss they can inspire,
معنى الضياع الذي يمكن أن توحي به،
so, too, I refuse and could not if I wished
لذا، أيضاً، أرفض ولا أستطيع حتى ولو رغبت
turn back the clock on an ever more closely knit, interdependent world,
أن أعيد عقارب الساعة لعالم أكثر تكافلاً وتماسكاً،
and on inventions that won't stop being invented.
والاختراعات التي لن تتوقف عن الاختراع.
And yet I must understand your experience of these things.
ورغم ذلك علي أن أفهم تجربتك بخصوص هذه الأشياء.
You have for years been telling me that your experience of these things
كنت تخبرني لسنين طويلة أن تجربتك في هذه الأشياء
is not as good as my theories forecast.
ليست جيدة كما تقول توقعات نظرياتي.
Yet before you could finish a complaining sentence
لكن قبل أن تنهي جملة تذمر
about the difficulty of living with erratic hours, volatile pay,
عن صعوبة العيش بوجود الساعات غير المنتظمة والأجر المتغير،
vanishing opportunities,
والفرص الضائعة،
about the pain of dropping your children off at 24-hour day care
وعن ألم وضع أطفالك في حضانة تعمل 24 ساعة
to make your 3am shift,
لكي تتمكن من الذهاب لوردية 3 صباحاً،
I shot back at you -- before you could finish your sentence --
أطلقت عليك--قبل أن تستطيع أن تنهي جملتك-
my dogma,
عقيدتي،
about how what you are actually experiencing was flexibility
كيف أن ما تعيشه الآن هو عبارة عن المرونة
and freedom.
والحرية.
Language is one of the only things that we truly share,
اللغة هي واحدة من الأشياء الوحيدة التي نتقاسمها حقاً،
and I sometimes used this joint inheritance
وأحيانا استعملت هذا الإرث المشترك
to obfuscate
لكي أشوش
and deflect
ولأنحرف
and justify myself;
ولأبرر نفسي،
to re-brand what was good for me
وإعادة تسمية ما كان مناسباً لي
as something appearing good for us both,
على أنه شيء ظاهرياً مناسب لكلينا،
when I threw around terms like "the sharing economy,"
حين أوزع مصطلحات من قبيل "الاقتصاد المشترك"،
and "disruption"
و "الزعزعة"
and "global resourcing."
و "المصادر العالمية"
I see now that what I was really doing,
أرى الآن ما كنت أقوم به حقاً،
at times,
أحياناً،
was buying your pain on the cheap,
أنني كنت أشتري ألمك بأرخص الأثمان،
sprucing it up
وأجمله
and trying to sell it back to you
ثم أحاول أن أبيعك إياه مرة أخرى
as freedom.
على أنها حرية.
I have wanted to believe and wanted you to believe
كنت أريد أن أؤمن، وكنت أريدك أن تؤمن
that the system that has been good to me,
أن النظام الذي كان مناسباً لي،
that has made my life ever more seamless,
والذي جعل حياتي أكثرسلاسة،
is also the best system for you.
أن هذا النظام هو الأفضل بالنسبة لك أيضاً.
I have condescended to you
لقد تنازلت لك
with the idea that you are voting against your economic interests --
مع فكرة أنك تصوت ضد مصالحك الاقتصادية--
voting against your interests,
تصوت ضد مصالحك،
as if I know your interests.
كما لو أني كنت أعرف مصالحك.
That is just my dogmatic economism talking.
كان ذلك فقط حديثي الاقتصادي المتحجر.
I have a weakness
لدي نقطة ضعف،
for treating people's economic interests as their only interest,
بأنني أتعامل مع المصالح الاقتصادية للناس على أنها اهتمامهم الوحيد،
ignoring things like belonging and pride
وأتجاهل أموراً مثل الانتماء والفخر
and the desire to send a message to those who ignore you.
والرغبة في إرسال رسالة لمن يتجاهلك.
So here we are,
ها نحن ذا،
in a scary but not inexplicable moment
في لحظة مخيفة لكن ليست صعبة الشرح
of demagoguery, fracture,
من الدهمة، والانكسار
xenophobia, resentment and fear.
ورهاب الأجانب، والاستياء والخوف.
And I worry for us both if we continue down this road,
وأنا قلق على كلينا، إن استمرينا في هذه الطريق،
me not listening,
أنا لست أنصت،
you feeling unheard,
وأنت تشعر بأنك غير مسموع،
you shouting to get me to listen.
وأنت تصرخ لتجعلني أنصت.
I worry when each of us is seduced by visions of the future
أنا قلق أن كلينا مفتون برؤى مستقبل
that have no place for the other.
ليس به مكان للآخر.
If this goes on,
إن استمر هذا،
there may be blood.
سيكون هناك دم.
There are already hints of this blood
هناك بوادرلهذا الدم أصلاً
in newspapers every day.
في الجرائد كل يوم.
There may be roundups, raids,
ربما هناك اعتقالات و قصف
deportations, camps, secessions.
وترحيل وملاجئ وانشقاقات.
And no, I do not think that I exaggerate.
وكلا، لا أعتقد أنني أبالغ.
There may be even talk of war
هناك حتى حديث عن الحرب
in places that were certain they were done with it.
في أماكن كان من الأكيد أنهم انتهوا منها.
There is always the hope of redemption.
هناك دائماً أمل في الخلاص.
But it will not be a cheap, shallow redemption
ولكنه لن يكون خلاصاُ رخيصاُ وسطحياُ،
that comes through blather about us all being in it together.
والذي يأتي من خلال الثرثرة عنا جميعاً كوننا مع بعضنا.
This will take more.
سيتطلب هذا شيئا أكبر.
It will take accepting that we both made choices to be here.
سيتطلب الأمر أننا سنقبل كلانا أننا اخترنا أن نكون هنا.
We create our "others."
نحن نخلق "الآخرين" منا.
As parents, as neighbors, as citizens,
كآباء وجيران ومواطنين،
we witness and sometimes ignore each other
نشهد على بعضنا وأحياناً نتجاهل بعضنا
into being.
في الوجود.
You were not born vengeful.
لم تولد مستعداً للانتقام.
I have some role
كان لدي بعض دور
in whatever thirst you now feel for revenge,
في أي عطش يراودك الآن للانتقام،
and that thirst now tempts me
وهذا العطش يغريني الآن
to plot ever more elaborate escapes
لأخطط هروباً متقنا أكثر
from our common life,
من حياتنا المشتركة،
from the schools and neighborhoods
من المدارس والأحياء
and airports and amusement parks
والمطارات وحدائق الترفيه
that we used to share.
التي اعتدنا تقاسمها.
We face, then,
نواجه، عندها،
a problem not of these large, impersonal forces.
مشكلاً ليس من جهة تلك القوات الكبرى غير المعروفة.
We face a problem of your and my relations.
نواجه مشكلاً يخص علاقاتك وعلاقاتي.
We chose ways of relating to each other
اخترنا طرقاً لنرى بعضنا البعض
that got us here.
والتي جلبتنا إلى هنا.
We can choose ways of relating
يمكننا أن نختار طرقاً للتعاطف
that get us out.
والتي ستخرجنا من هنا.
But there are things we might have to let go of,
ولكن هناك أشياء علينا أن نتخلى عنها،
fellow citizen,
مواطني العزيز،
starting with our own cherished versions of reality.
بدءاً من نسخ واقعنا المحتفى بها.
Imagine if you let go of fantasies
تخيل لو أنك تخليت عن التخيلات
of a society purged of these or those people.
عن مجتمع مطهر من هؤلاء أو أولئك الناس.
Imagine if I let go of my habit
تخيل لو أنني أتخلى عن عادتي
of saving the world behind your back,
في إنقاذ العالم دون علمك،
of deliberating on the future
وصنع المستقبل
of your work,
عملك،
your food,
وطعامك،
your schools,
ومدارسك،
in places where you couldn't get past security.
في الأماكن التي لا يمكنك فيها تجاوز الحاجز الأمني.
We can do this only if we first accept
يمكننا القيام بهذا فقط حين نتقبل أولاً
that we have neglected each other.
أننا تجاهلنا بعضنا البعض.
If there is hope to summon
إن كان هناك أمل في استجماع القوى
in this ominous hour,
في هذه الساعة المشؤومة،
it is this.
فهي هذه.
We have, for too long,
لقد ركضنا لوقت طويل
chased various shimmering dreams
وراء أحلام براقة متنوعة
at the cost of attention to the foundational dream of each other,
ودفعنا ثمن الاهتمام بالحلم الأساسي لبعضنا البعض،
the dream of tending to each other,
حلم ميلنا لبعضنا البعض،
of unleashing each other's wonders,
وإطلاق العنان لتساؤلاتنا،
of moving through history together.
حول المضي قدماً عبر التاريخ معاً.
We could dare to commit to the dream of each other
كان بإمكاننا أن نجرؤ على الإلتزام بحلم ببعضنا البعض
as the thing that matters before every neon thing.
على أنه الشيء الأهم قبل أي شيء آخر.
Let us dare.
فلنجرؤ.
Sincerely yours,
مع كامل ودي،
a fellow citizen.
من مواطن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)